在非洲的中心
Here, in the heart of Africa,
这片辽阔的大陆上
lives one of this great continent's
生活着最特别却被误解的动物
most extraordinary yet misunderstood animals.
这种动物依赖卓越的团队合作
Animals that only thrive through remarkable team work,
以及领袖的力量与本领繁衍生息
and through the strength and skill of their leaders.
杂色狼  曾被称为非洲野犬
Painted wolves, once known as Cape Hunting Dogs,
是非洲最濒危的捕食者之一
are one of Africa's most threatened predators.
狼群需要大面积的狩猎领地
Their packs require huge areas of territory in which to hunt.
但如今  来自于人类的压力
But today, because of human pressure,
使得它们的世界迅速缩小
their world is shrinking fast.
领地相邻的邻居
And whereas once neighbours
曾经可以相对和平地共处
could live together in relative peace,
如今  它们之间的竞争十分激烈
today there is intense rivalry between them.
在两年多的时间里
For more than two years,
我们在津巴布韦马纳波尔斯的团队
our team here in Mana Pools in Zimbabwe,
一直在追踪
have been following the fortunes
仅剩的几大家族之一的命运
of one of the last great families.
开始拍摄时
We join them at a moment
一位母亲与它其中一个女儿的竞争
when competition between mother and one of her daughters
正愈演愈烈
is boiling up,
不仅威胁到长久以来的和平
threatening to not only shatter a long-established peace,
更有可能分裂整个家族
but to tear apart the whole family.
杂色狼
这是泰特  统治这个家族的女王
This is Tait, the family's ruling queen.
它即是母亲  也是祖母
She's a mother and a grandmother.
多年以来  家族不断扩大
For years, she has used her position
它用自己的地位维持家族内部的和平
to keep the peace within her sprawling family.
但泰特现已衰老
But Tait is now old.
它的势力逐渐衰减
Her powers are waning.
泰特仍掌控着最佳的狩猎领地
Tait still controls the very best hunting territory,
赞比西河两岸富足的土地
the rich lands on the banks of the Zambezi.
但它被包围了
But she's surrounded.
东方是危险的狮群领地
To the east lie the dangerous lion pridelands.
南方是鬣狗聚居的森林
To the south, forests full of hyena.
而西方
And to the west,
是泰特的一个女儿黑蒂领导的狼群
a pack led by one of Tait's daughters, Blacktip.
多年以来  黑蒂与它的母亲
For many years, Blacktip has lived in peaceful coexistence
和平共处
with her mother,
双方都有足够的领地赖以生存
each with enough territory to survive.
但黑蒂的狼群愈发壮大
But Blacktip's pack has grown huge.
目前成员已达三十条
It's now 30 strong.
有生以来第一次  它需要更大的领地
For the first time, she needs more territory
来养活壮大的家族
if she's to feed her growing family.
通常  女儿不会侵略母亲的领地
Normally, a daughter would not invade her mother's territory.
然而  鬣狗统治南方
However, with hyenas ruling to the south,
人类占据西方的狩猎区域
and humans having taken the hunting lands to the west,
黑蒂别无选择
Blacktip has no choice
只能着眼东方
but to turn her sights east,
向它母亲的领地扩张
towards her mother's lands.
一场晨猎之后
Where, after a morning's hunt,
泰特和它的狼群正在休息
Tait and her pack are resting.
黑蒂的狼群比它母亲的
Blacktip's pack outnumbers her mother's
规模大一倍多
by more than two to one.
一场伏击
An ambush!
逆境重重
Against these odds,
泰特无能为力
Tait is powerless.
撤退是唯一的选择
Retreat is the only option.
从此这里成了黑蒂的领地
This has now become Blacktip's territory.
这场战斗短暂却血腥
A brief but bloody battle.
泰特和它的狼群如今无家可归
Tait and her pack are now homeless.
它向东撤退
She retreats eastwards.
但那里是危险区域
But this is dangerous country.
这条河是它原本的领地
This river marks the boundary between her old territory
与狮群领地的分界
and the lion pridelands.
在它漫长的一生中
In her long life,
泰特探索过马纳的每个角落
Tait has explored every part of Mana.
它知道在这里安家太过危险
She knows that this is too perilous a place to make a home.
狮子会搜捕猎杀杂色狼幼崽
Lions will search out and kill puppies,
若有机会  甚至会猎杀成年杂色狼
and even adults, if they get the chance.
目前这是唯一可以藏身的地方
For now, it's the only place to hide.
但泰特必须保护家族的安全
But Tait must keep her family safe,
避开那二十六头统治此地的狮子
well away from the 26 lions that rule here.
黑蒂抢夺领地已过去三个月
Three months have passed since Blacktip's takeover.
这片领地如今被它牢牢掌控
And all these lands are now firmly under her control.
黑蒂的狼群花费大量时间进行气味标记
Blacktip's pack have spent a great deal of time scent marking,
为它们的新领地确立边界
establishing their new territorial boundaries.
黑蒂和它的家族
And Blacktip and her family
从曾是它母亲的领地获取了丰富的食物
have fed well on what was her mother's lands.
但现在旱季来临  地形发生变化
But now, it's the dry season, and the landscape is changing.
对于靠速度取胜的猎手来说  地面布满危险
The ground is dangerous for hunters who rely on speed.
大象在淤泥中留下的深陷足印
Deep footprints left by elephants in soft mud
被烤得如石头一般坚硬
have baked as hard as rock.
杂色狼只要踏错一步
And a painted wolf putting a foot wrong
就可能身受重伤
could seriously damage itself.
黑斑羚能跃过地面深陷的坑
The impalas' ability to leap over the worst of the pot holes
这如今成为优势
now gives them an edge.
在这种情况下
In these conditions,
黑蒂的狼群将很难捕到食物
Blacktip's pack will find it hard to feed themselves.
但狼群的规模和力量
But the size and strength of the pack
或许能让它捕猎一种全新的猎物
might enable her to catch a totally new kind of prey.
大个的公狒狒十分强壮
A large male baboon is strong,
体重接近杂色狼的两倍
almost twice the weight of a painted wolf.
它们还有巨大的犬齿
And armed with huge canine teeth.
黑蒂狼群庞大的规模
The great size of Blacktip's pack
让公狒狒无力保护全员
means the large males can't defend their troupe
顾此失彼
against them all.
食物来之不易
The meal has been hard-won.
不过发现这个新机会的
But discovering this new possibility
时机恰到好处
has come at just the right time.
黑蒂在与泰特的领地争夺中
Blacktip won more than just hunting lands
不仅赢得更大的狩猎区域
in her battle to claim Tait's territory.
还占据了马纳波尔斯养育幼崽
She secured the safest place to raise puppies
最安全的地方
in all of Mana Pools.
果然  黑蒂产下五只嗷嗷待哺的幼崽
And sure enough, blacktip has a new litter of five hungry pups.
今天它们的父亲负责照料它们
Their father is babysitting them today.
它们都急切盼望狩猎队归来
Everyone is impatient for the return of the hunting party.
等待期间  幼崽发现
While they wait, the pups discover
世界远比它们的狼群更为广大
that there's more to the world than just their pack.
奇怪的巨兽
Strange giants.
黑蒂没空喘息
There's no rest for Blacktip.
它不仅要带领狩猎征程
She not only leads the hunting trips,
作为雌性首领  它还是唯一生育
but, as the alpha female, she's the only who breeds
并分泌乳汁的母狼
and provides milk for the pups.
现在除了乳汁
It's not just milk.
幼崽已经急不可待地开始吃肉
They're already eagerly eating meat.
黑蒂掌控泰特的领地是值得的
Blacktip's hold on Tait's territory appears to be paying off.
泰特和它的狼群被流放
It has been four months
进入狮群领地
since Tait and her pack were forced into exile
已有四个月
here in the lion pridelands.
与它原本的领地相比  这里不仅更危险
Compared to her home territory, there is not only more danger,
而且猎物更稀少
but there's much less prey.
令人惊叹的是  即便如此
Yet, remarkably, even here,
泰特还是保住了狼群全员的性命
Tait has managed to keep every member of her pack alive.
不过现在它却不见踪影
But she is nowhere to be seen.
家族里的其它成员
The rest of her family
都守在一个废弃的食蚁兽洞穴附近
are waiting close to an abandoned aardvark burrow.
原来如此
And this is why.
过去三周  泰特都藏在地下洞穴里
Tait has spent the last three weeks hidden underground.
尽管困难重重  它还是产下了
She has managed, against the odds,
它的第八窝幼崽
to produce her eighth litter.
两只幼崽第一次出现
Two tiny puppies emerge for the very first time.
蜜獾
Honey badgers.
它们恶名昭彰地好斗
They are notoriously aggressive,
对幼崽来说是威胁
and a danger to the pups.
泰特最小的女儿  塔米  从未见过蜜獾
Tait's youngest daughter, Tammy, has never seen one before.
但是本能告诉它要赶走它们
But her instinct tells her to drive them away.
泰特借此机会
And this gives Tait the chance
把幼崽安全地带回洞穴里
to get her pups to safety underground.
今年  泰特和黑蒂
This year, both Tait and Blacktip
产下的幼崽都比往年少很多
have produced far fewer puppies than ever before.
也许这标志着
Perhaps this is the first sign
两个狼群之间的冲突
that the conflict between the two packs
开始威胁到整个家族的未来
is threatening the future of the entire family.
每天两次
Twice a day,
泰特要带领它的狩猎队踏上危险的征途
Tait has to lead her hunting party on a risky journey
前往赞比西河河岸  猎物在那里聚集
to the banks of the Zambezi river, where the prey gather.
但那里也正是
But it is also the very heart
狮子领地的中心
of lion territory.
它必须不被察觉地带它们潜入
She must sneak them into position undetected.
然后最好速战速决
Then, it's in and out as fast as possible.
狼群需要快速行动
The pack need to work fast.
所有辛劳只换来几口果腹之食
All that effort for a few mouthfuls of food.
今天幼崽要挨饿了
The puppies will go hungry today.
雪上加霜
And the pack has been dealt another blow.
又是塔米  泰特最小的女儿
Again it's Tammy, Tait's youngest daughter,
发现了问题
who spots the problem.
塔米的姐姐倒下了
Tammy's sister has fallen.
它绊倒在大象的足印坑里  摔断了一条腿
She has broken a leg stumbling into an elephant's footprint.
对大多数动物来说  这意味着死亡
For most animals, this would be the end.
但这个家族不会抛下它自生自灭
But the family won't just leave her to fend for herself.
杂色狼也许比任何其它动物
Painted wolves, perhaps more than any other animal,
都更照顾老弱病残的成员
care for pack members who are old or injured.
在它不能参与狩猎期间
Tait's family will protect and feed her
泰特的家族会保护并养活它
while she herself cannot join in the hunt.
旱季变成干旱
The dry season turns to drought.
水牛群在迁徙
The great buffalo herds are on the move.
食物和水变得越来越匮乏
Food and water are becoming increasingly scarce.
如今马纳的所有居民汇集至赞比西河
AlI of Mana's inhabitants are now drawn towards the Zambezi
及其沿岸仅剩的几个水塘
and the few pools that remain along its banks.
干旱也意味着黑蒂和它的幼崽
The drought also means that it's time for Blacktip and her pups
该离开它们的巢穴了
to leave their den behind.
对幼崽来说  这是第一次冒险
For the pups, this is their first adventure.
现在幼崽已经可以跟上成年狼群
Now the pups are old enough to follow the adults,
黑蒂可以继续标记领地的新边界
Blacktip can resume marking the new boundaries of her territory
以巩固它的占领
to consolidate her takeover.
在最远的东部边界
On the far eastern borders,
黑蒂闻到一个熟悉的气味
Blacktip picks up a familiar scent.
气味陈旧  但是毋庸置疑
It's old, but unmistakable.
是它的母亲
Her mother.
这一发现对黑蒂影响巨大
This discovery has an extraordinary effect on Blacktip.
它能从中判断泰特行进的方向
She can tell from this smell which direction Tait took.
黑蒂不再标记领地
Blacktip stops territorial marking
而是开始追踪它的母亲
and instead sets off in pursuit of her mother.
看来黑蒂要尽力把泰特永远地
It seems that Blacktip is going to try and drive Tait out of Mana
逐出马纳
once and for all.
但是踏入未知地域
But she's taking a huge risk
它冒了巨大的风险
by going into territory she doesn't know.
鬣狗
Hyenas.
月黑风高夜  狼群通常会找安全地点
On moonless nights, the pack would normally rest up
休息到天亮
somewhere safe until dawn.
但这一次  黑蒂带领它们
But instead, Blacktip leads them,
步入黑暗
marching on into the gloom.
谁也不想在黑暗中掉队
No one wants to be the straggler in the dark.
夜间这个家族聚得更紧
The family bunch together much more closely at night.
现在  十五条鬣狗在跟踪它们
And now, 15 hyenas are tracking them.
进攻也许是最好的防御手段
Attack may be the best form of defense.
黑蒂以为它占据上风
Blacktip thinks she's got the upper hand,
可是它让幼崽落单了
but she's let her pups get separated.
幼崽没了
The puppy is lost.
低头垂尾  它们似乎在哀悼
Heads down, tails down, they seem to mourn.
它们沉默地行进数小时
For hours, they march in silence.
气氛庄严
A solemn procession.
尽管痛失幼崽  黑蒂依然带领狼群前进
Despite her loss, Blacktip drives her pack on,
远远越过泰特原本的领地边界
far beyond the boundary of Tait's old territory.
追踪母亲  它来到从未踏足过的地方
Tracking her mother into a place she's never been before,
深入狮群领地的中心
deep into the heart of the lion pridelands.
令人惊叹的是
Tait, remarkably,
泰特已在狮口下保护它的狼群
has now managed to keep her pack safe from the lions
长达八个月
for eight months.
它受伤的女儿在康复中
Her injured daughter is on the mend.
在它恢复期间  这个家族一直在保护它
The family have been protecting her while she recovers.
它们能活下来
They only survive here
靠得是一刻也不松懈的警惕
by being on constant alert for signs of danger.
今天风中散发着危险的气味
And today it is the wind that carries a warning.
黑蒂要来了
Blacktip is coming.
得到预警  泰特不打算冒险迎战
Forewarned, Tait isn't going to risk an attack.
狼群掉头逃跑
The pack turns tail and runs.
气温达到五十摄氏度
The temperature has reached 50 degrees.
可黑蒂还是带领狼群穷追不舍
Still, Blacktip pushes her pack on in pursuit.
它们逼近泰特  距离不到两千米
They're closing in, less than a mile behind Tait.
但最终  高温难以招架
But, finally, the heat is just too much.
黑蒂被迫停止追赶
Blacktip is forced to call a halt.
但是危险正在迫近
But danger is approaching.
狼群被打散
The pack has scattered!
狮子们因而可以专挑幼狼来攻击
And now the lions will try to pick off the puppies.
只有一条成年杂色狼与幼狼们在一起
There's only one adult with the pups.
那不足以保护它们
That won't be enough to save them.
但这个也许能
But this might.
水牛和狮子的冲突时刻不断
Buffaloes and ions are always in conflict.
只身冲入狮群是非常少见的
To charge in alone is very unusual.
但是它的确是救了幼狼们
But it's certainly saved the pups.
黑蒂和狼群的追踪被迫终止
Blacktip and her pack have been halted in their tracks.
黑蒂对泰特的追击
Blacktip's pursuit of Tait
把它的族群暴露于太多的危险之中
has exposed her family to too many dangers,
风险太大了
too many risks.
族群虽想竭力施以援手
The pack are desperate to help,
但是它们实在无能为力
but there is nothing they can do.
对泰特的追击彻底终结
The pursuit of Tait is over.
黑蒂的族群逃了
Blacktip's pack run.
它们逃啊逃啊
They run, and run.
逃过一沟又一壑
Mile after mile.
幼狼们紧跟着
Puppies in tow.
日夜兼程
All through the day, all through the night.
一直回到了家园
All the way home.
它们放弃了夺取的领地
The territory they stole, abandoned.
冲突结束了
The conflict is over.
代价太惨重了
It cost too much.
泰特和它的族群能感觉出黑蒂的撤退
Tait and her pack can already sense Blacktip's retreat.
从冲突爆发以来
For the first time since the beginning of the conflict,
它们第一次放松了下来
they appear relaxed.
很快它们敏锐的嗅觉
Soon, their keen sense of smell
就会告诉它们  被夺去的领地已经被放弃了
will tell them their stolen territory is no longer occupied.
用不了多久
It won't be long until it's time
泰特的族群也要回家了
for Tait's pack to also go home.
但是泰特不会跟它们一起回去了
But Tait will not be joining them.
在长达七年半的时间里
For seven-and-a-half years,
它一直是它们的领袖  它们的女王
she's been their leader, their matriarch.
如今它们的流亡行将结束
And now, as their exile finally draws to a close,
它确保了它的族群还能继续生存
she has ensured her pack still have a future,
真正有机会重拾故土
a real chance to reclaim their old territory.
就在它的族群终于可以回家的时候
Before her pack could, at last, head home,
无情的岁月终于找上了泰特
age finally caught up with Tait.
年纪太过老迈  动作过于迟缓
Too old, too slow,
它已经无法躲避狮子
she was no longer able to evade the lions.
它的雄性伴侣拒绝放弃它
Her alpha male refused to abandon her.
它们一起死在了狮群领地里
Together, they died in the pridelands.
泰特的族群群龙无首
Tait's pack are left leaderless.
但是故事并没有随着泰特的去世而结束
But the story doesn't end with Tait's passing.
滋养万物的雨水在干旱之后来了
Life-giving rains follow the drought.
曾经的艰难时刻很快因富庶充盈被淡忘
Hard times are quickly forgotten in times of plenty.
而故事再次出现转折
And the story takes another twist.
在回家的路上
On their way home,
泰特的族群吸引到了一队游荡的雄性杂色狼
Tait's pack attract a band of roving males.
随着生力军的增援
And with these reinforcements,
它们不但收复了一部分泰特从前的领地
they not only reclaim some of Tait's old territory,
而且还上演了一场以前从未被看到的仪式
but also perform a ritual never witnessed before.
它们以这种令人难以忘记的叫声
With these haunting calls,
来选择新的领袖
they are choosing their new leader.
泰特的血脉有机会得以延续
And the chance to continue Tait's bloodline.
六个月后
Six months later,
隐秘的森林深处
hidden away in a secluded part of the forest,
七条小幼崽现身了
a litter of seven tiny puppies.
它们的母亲塔米是泰特最小的女儿
They're born to Tammy, Tait's youngest daughter,
现在是泰特王位的继承者
and now heir to Tait's throne.
新生命的到来以及新来的雄性杂色狼的加入
With these new arrivals, and the new males,
使得泰特原来的族群恢复到了二十三个成员
Tait's old pack has bounced back to 23 members.
塔米现在率领的族群
Tammy now leads a pack that is once again
再一次成为一股不能被忽视的力量
a force to be reckoned with.
而在西面  冲突早已成为历史
Back in the west, with the conflict long over,
黑蒂自己也产下十只健康的幼崽
Blacktip has produced 10 healthy puppies of her own.
泰特王朝终于重新归于平衡
Balance has finally been restored to Tait's dynasty.
全世界仅存六千六百只杂色狼
There are only 6,600 painted wolves left in the world.
截止目前我们记录了
To date, we count 280 descendants
两百八十只具有泰特的血脉
from Tait's bloodline.
泰特对这个种群的存续
Tait's contribution to the survival
做出了无可匹敌的贡献
of this species is unparalleled.
它的王朝是稳固的
Her dynasty feels secure.
至少现在如此
For now, at least.